Guide to the Stephen Timoshenko Papers SC0641
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stephen Timoshenko papers
1907-1996
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Timoshenko, Stephen
SC0641
8.25 Linear Feet
Correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, galleys, notes, reprints, photographs, passports, awards, and other items; some materials are in Russian or German. Correspondents include Dr. L. Prandtl, Cyril O. Rhys, Gunhard Orovas, Elena Zagustin, and William F. Durand.. His typescript articles are largely on mechanical stresses and date from ca. 1907 to 1940, with some in Russian; there is also a typescript biographical essay on James Victor Uspensky, ca. 1947. Other items of note include a scrapbook (in Russian) with some photographs possibly from a trip to Russia in 1958; his report to Westinghouse on visits to European laboratories, 1934; and Esther Kaletzky's remarks at the First International Conference of Women Engineers and Scientists, June 1964. Additional papers added in 2009 pertain to the Timoshenko book collection in Stanford’s Engineering Library but also include copies of Gregory Timoshenko’s "Letters to My Grandchildren," 1983-90, which include information on his father, Stephen Timoshenko.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Administrative transfer from Engineering Library, 1998-2009.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Stephen Prokofievitch Timoshenko, a world-renowned authority on theoretical and applied mechanics, was educated at the Munich Polytechnic Institute and at the University of Gottingen. He taught at the Polytechnic Institute of Kiev (1907-11) and the Polytechnic Institute of St. Petersburg (1912-17), before fleeing Russia for Yugoslavia. He taught at the University of Zagreb from 1920 to 1922, and then moved to the United States. He was a research engineer at Westinghouse and taught at the University of Michigan before joining the Stanford faculty in 1936. Although he officially retired in 1944 he continued to teach and write. His best known works include STRENGTH OF MATERIALS, THEORY OF ELASTICITY, and ENGINEERING MECHANICS.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, galleys, notes, reprints, photographs, passports, awards, and other items; some materials are in Russian or German. Correspondents include Dr. L. Prandtl, Cyril O. Rhys, Gunhard Orovas, Elena Zagustin, and William F. Durand.. His typescript articles are largely on mechanical stresses and date from ca. 1907 to 1940, with some in Russian; there is also a typescript biographical essay on James Victor Uspensky, ca. 1947. Other items of note include a scrapbook (in Russian) with some photographs possibly from a trip to Russia in 1958; his report to Westinghouse on visits to European laboratories, 1934; and Esther Kaletzky's remarks at the First International Conference of Women Engineers and Scientists, June 1964. Additional papers added in 2009 pertain to the Timoshenko book collection in Stanford's Engineering Library but also include copies of Gregory Timoshenko's "Letters to My Grandchildren," 1983-90, which include information on his father, Stephen Timoshenko.
Mechanics, Applied.; Structural analysis (Engineering).; Prandtl, Ludwig; Kaletzky, Esther.; Zagustin, Elena.; Durand, William Frederick; Timoshenko, Stephen; Timoshenko, Gregory.; Timoshenko, Stephen
- Papers
  - Biography (assorted articles) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical articles (in Russian, French, German) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Award of the James Watt International Medal to Professor Stepan Timoshenko, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Honorary degree, University of Bologna--text of presentation and photo, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Franklin Institute, Report investigating the work of Stephen P. Timoshenko, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Portrait of Timoshenko by Jack Kraft for National Cyclopedia of American Biography (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Identity paper, Zagreb, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Visas, 1919-20, and letter from Prof. Dr. L. Prandtl, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Passport, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Westinghouse--letter and contract 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 60th Birthday greetings, 1938-39 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 75th Birthday dinner program, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 90th Birthday greetings, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs (mostly portraits of ST) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs for "As I Remember" (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs for "As I Remember" (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photo negatives of Russian buildings (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs, 1920s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photographs, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photographs, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Printing plate of 1947 photograph (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Photographs, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photographs, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photographs, identified, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Photographs, Russian, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Photographs, unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Buckling of thin plates under compressive and shearing stresses" – manuscript in Russian, ca. 1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Bending Stresses in Curved Tubes of Rectangular Cross-section" – manuscript and reprint, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The static deflection and vibrations of circular diaphragms," typescripts, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Stiffness of suspension bridges," 1928 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Long Circular Tubes Submitted to Uniform External Pressure" – typescript, post-1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "James Victor Uspensky"--typescript, ca. 1947 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Review of Beams on Elastic Foundation by Hetenyi, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "The use of the Rayleigh method for the calculation of the period of free vibrations in crankshafts"--typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript of "Article 1" with letters, 1928 [publisher], 1942 [Prof. V. Mises, in German] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript of "Article 2" (mostly formulas, computations), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript of "Article 3" (formulas, computations), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript of "Article 5" (formulas, computations), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript of "Article 7" (formulas, computations, figures), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript of "Article 8" (stiffening truss variable cross section), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Engineering Dept. Report, Westinghouse (on presenting papers at 2 European conferences), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Engineer’s Trip Report, Westinghouse (on visits to various European laboratories), 1934 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lecture notes, stability, Los Angeles, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Reprints, 1921-24 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Reprints, 1925-29 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Reprints, 1932-38 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Reprints, 1941-47 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Reprints in Russian (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Notebooks (2 small volumes, in several languages) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Address book (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rhys, Cyril O.--correspondence, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Timoshenko, Sergius--correspondence about, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence re his articles, 1927-48 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, general, 1945-69 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters in Russian, 1921-63 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Agreement re publication, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Airey, John R., "The Vibrations of Circular Plates and their Relation to Bessel Functions"--manuscript but noted as from Proceedings of the Physical Society of London, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Euler, Leonhard--reprint with correspondence (both in Russian), 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Prof. Finch’s speech "In Memoriam: Boris Alexandre Bakhmeteff" ca. 1951 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Klitchieff, J. M., "Torsion Eines I Traegers"--typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Malkin, I.--article and accompanying note, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Mehlhorn, Gerhard--dissertation with note, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Oravas, Gunhard--correspondence re revision of their book Strength of Materials, 1964-70 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Oravas, Gunhard--text for revised edition (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sakadi, Zyuro, "Criticism on the Equations of Flexural Vibration of a Thin Bar"--typescript, 1920s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Timoshenko, J. A.--reprint, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Zagustin, Elena--article (Stability of an elastic ring in a rigid cavity) and letter to Timoshenko (in Russian), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Discussions of Timoshenko papers (typescripts, n.d.) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Newcomen Society, printed matter, 1938-39 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Russian items found in envelope, 1954-56 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Soviet scientists--clippings, 1936-44 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Timoshenko, Gregory--biography (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - International Union of Theoretical and Applied Mechanics (IUTAM), 1938-71 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook (items in Russian) with some photographs, possibly from trip to Russia in1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Certificates, honors and awards, 1928-67 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, honors and awards (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 80th Birthday greetings (in Russian), 1958 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Passports, visas, etc. 1914-22 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Passports, visas, etc. 1917-26 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Passports, visas, etc. 1920-26 (in many languages, some may be letters) (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "The Approximate Solution of Two-Dimensional Problems of Elasticity" – typescript, ca. 1920 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "On Stresses in a Plate with a Circular Hole"--typescript with cover letter, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Notes, manuscript, in Russian (?), ca. 1927 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Typescripts and manuscripts in Russian (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Kaletzky, Esther, her remarks at First International Conference of Women Engineers and Scientists, June 1964 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Steinhardt, Jng. O., "Friedrich Engesser," 1949 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Grigoliouk, Edward I.--correspondence about (in English and Russian) 1965-67 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Letter to Timoshenko with a typescript article in Russian, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Pre-stressed concrete, printed materials (in French) with photographs from a construction site (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Golden Gate Bridge and SF Bay Bridge, materials on, 1933-34 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Timoshenko and McCullough, Elements of Strength of Materials (2nd edition) (Box 6)
  - Timoshenko and Young, Engineering Mechanics (2nd edition) (Box 6)
  - Theory of Elasticity, galleys (part 1) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Theory of Elasticity, galleys (part 2) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Theory of Elasticity, galleys (part 3) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--A (Box 6, Folder 4)
    General note
    (includes Bo Adamson and Army-Navy-Commerce Committee on Aircraft Requirements "Strength of Aircraft Elements" 1938)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--B (Box 6, Folder 5)
    (includes C. Bienzeno, P. G. Bordoni, N. Bogolioubov, Gh. Buzdugan, and A. Brandt)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--C-D (Box 6, Folder 6)
    (includes Fo-Van Chang, A. D. de Pater, W. J. Duncan, and J. Dorr)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--E (Box 6, Folder 7)
    (S. Eggwertz and W. Ermakoff)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--F (Box 7, Folder 1)
    (includes Max Frocht, O. Foppl, E. Forslind and J. M. Frankland)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--G (Box 7, Folder 2)
    (includes A. Grudemo, H. G. Ganev, and R. Grammel)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--H (Box 7, Folder 3)
    (includes M. Hetenyi, R. Hedin, and L. M. Hoskins)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--Hedberg, John ("Mechanics of Fluids" 1940) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--Junkers-Flugzeugwerk (Box 7, Folder 5)
    (catalogs of airplanes, in German and English)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--K (Box 7, Folder 6)
    (includes K. Kammuller, C. F. Kollbrunner, W. T. Koiter, and P. N. Kamenev)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--L (Box 7, Folder 7)
    (includes G. Lindh and E. H. Lee)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--Ma (Box 7, Folder 8)
    (includes J. Marin, Ch. Massonnet, and L. C. Maugh)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--Me-N (Box 8, Folder 1)
    (includes I. V. Mesherskii, I. E. Mouromtseff, F. Niordson, and J. Nowinski)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--O-P (Box 8, Folder 2)
    (includes A. E. Olivares, M. Picone, H. Pallmann, P. Pedersen, A. Pucher, and J. Podolsky)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--Popov, E. P. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--R (Box 8, Folder 4)
    (includes H. S. Richmond and T. G. Rogers)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--S-T (Box 8, Folder 5)
    (includes M. Sayir, E. Sergent, Ship Structure Committee, A. N. Sakoff, L. Tichvinsky "Notes to a Grandson," and L. Tetmajer)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--W-Z (Box 8, Folder 6)
    (includes booklet of papers from Seminar in Honor of Vladimir K. Zworykin held at Princeton)
  - Reprints, articles, etc. by others--Zagustin, Elena (thesis and dissertation) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Printing films of illustrations for Theory of Elasticity (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Illustrations for Theory of Elasticity (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Illustrations for book by Hetenyi [title not noted], John Wiley publisher #1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Illustrations for book by Hetenyi [title not noted], John Wiley publisher #2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Illustrations for book by Hetenyi [title not noted], John Wiley publisher #3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Plaque presented by the Stanford School of Engineering to Timoshenko in honor of his contribution as a member of the faculty (Box 9)
  - Assorted books and reprints in Russian and books by other authors (Box 10)
  - Assorted diplomas and certificates in several languages (Box 11)
  - Certificates, 1927-44 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Second International Congress for Applied Mechanics, program, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Third International Congress for Applied Mechanics, program, list of attendees, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Fifth International Congress for Applied Mechanics, programs, invitations, and a letter from H. M. Westergaard, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Letter from W. S. Rugg (Westinghouse) re position with clipping, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous items, 1866-1953 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Timoshenko’s Ph.D. thesis (photostatic copy) 1905 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - University of Michigan degree (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Book jackets (from books by Timoshenko) (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Bridget, F. J., C. C. Jerome and A. B. Vosseller, "Some New Experiments on Buckling of Thin Wall Construction, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Donnell, L. H., correspondence and two articles on thin-walled cylinders, 1933 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Durand, W. F., letter to Timoshenko with copy of letter from Admiral Cook and 3 documents regarding plans for an airplane carrier airship, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Timoshenko (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Richardson, L. F. The Approximate Arithmetical Solution by Finite Differences of Physical Problems Involving differential Equations, with an Application to the Stresses in a Masonry Dam [reprint], 1910 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Saab Technical Note "Proposed program for buckling of dural and alclad sheet in the creep region," 1955 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Timoshenko, Theory of Bending, Torsion and Buckling of Thin-walled Members of Open Cross Section [reprint], 1945 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Timoshenko book in Russian, with letter (in English) from G. Pisarenko regarding events in honor of Timoshenko in the Ukraine, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2009-093
  - Acknowledgement of Gift, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical articles (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Catalog of the Timoshenko Collection [books], first draft, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and memos, 1966-72 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and memos, 1982-83 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and memos, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and memos, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and memos, 1986-87, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Floor Plan 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gregory Timoshenko, Letters to My Grandchildren, 1983-90 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Socrates List of Timoshenko books, Aug. 5, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Timoshenko books in Special Collections, July 23, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Unused book barcodes (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2017-297
  - Timoshenko, "Theory of Elasticity", 1934 (Box 1)
  - Timoshenko correspondence found in "Theory of Elasticity", 1935, 1957 (Box 1)